<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Two assize sermons preached at Bridgnorth for the county of Salop in the year 1657. The first, upon Psalm 58. verse 1. Doe you indeed speak righteousnesse, o congregation? Doe ye judge uprightly, o ye sonnes of men? The second, upon Psalm 37. verse 37. Marke the perfect man, and behold the upright: for the end of that man is peace? / By Mich. Thomas; rector of Stockton in the same county.</title>
            <author>Thomas, Michael, rector of Stockton.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1659</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 99 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 73 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A95723</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T970</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1790_1</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R209682</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99868548</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99868548</idno>
            <idno type="VID">170373</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A95723)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 170373)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 223:E1790[1])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Two assize sermons preached at Bridgnorth for the county of Salop in the year 1657. The first, upon Psalm 58. verse 1. Doe you indeed speak righteousnesse, o congregation? Doe ye judge uprightly, o ye sonnes of men? The second, upon Psalm 37. verse 37. Marke the perfect man, and behold the upright: for the end of that man is peace? / By Mich. Thomas; rector of Stockton in the same county.</title>
                  <author>Thomas, Michael, rector of Stockton.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12], 62, [2], 63-128 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by W. Wilson for Humphrey Moseley, and are to bee sold at his shop, at the Prince's Armes in S. Paul's Church-yard.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1659.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Each sermon has separate dated title page; register and pagination are continuous.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "June".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Psalms CVIII, 1 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Psalms XXXVII, 37 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:170373:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p> TWO ASSIZE SERMONS Preached at <hi>Bridgnorth</hi> for the County of <hi>Salop</hi> in the year 1657.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>The firſt, upon Pſalm 58. verſe 1.</bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>Doe you indeed ſpeak Righteouſneſſe, O Congregation?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Doe ye judge uprightly, O ye ſonnes of men?</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>The ſecond, upon Pſalm 37. verſe 37.</bibl> 
               <hi>Marke the perfect man, and behold the upright: For the end of that man is peace?</hi>
            </q>
            <p>By MICH. THOMAS;</p>
            <p>Rector of <hi>Stockton</hi> in the ſame COUNTY.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>W. Wilſon</hi> for <hi>Humphrey Moſeley,</hi> and are to bee ſold at his Shop, at the <hi>Prince</hi>'s <hi>Armes</hi> in S. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-yard. 1659.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:170373:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:170373:3"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:170373:3"/>
                  <p> A SERMON, Preached at the ASSIZES Held at BRIDGNORTH For the County of <hi>Salop</hi> in the year, 1657.</p>
                  <p>On the Firſt day of the Aſſizes, By <hi>Mich: Thomas,</hi> Rector of <hi>Sockton</hi> in the ſame COUNTY.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Humphrey Moſeley</hi> at the <hi>Prince</hi>'s <hi>Armes</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-yard. 1659.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:170373:4"/>
               </div>
               <div type="dedication">
                  <pb facs="tcp:170373:4"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>TO MY WORTHY FRIEND MAJOR</hi> EDMUND WARING.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>SIR,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen the Command of the Power of this County, both Civill and Military, was committed to your care and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagement; you were pleaſed to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe a little of that power you had over me, in deſiring me (and your deſires are commands) accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to my Function, to attend upon the Judges.</p>
                  <p>You cannot but ſay, you found
<pb facs="tcp:170373:5"/> me both willing &amp; obedient. And I undertook the work, upon a threefold encouragement.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>Firſt, as it was a Service to your Selfe.</item>
                     <item>Secondly, as it was a Service to my Country.</item>
                     <item>Thirdly, as it was a Service to the Lord.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p>For your ſelfe; I am glad that I have occaſion to make this pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like profeſſion, that I am very ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible of thoſe great Civilities, I have received from you. I know, that, by the laws of Friendſhip, where there are receits, there ſhould be returnes; which though they do not anſwer in proportion, are yet compleated by their inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
                  <p>I have alwayes thought, That to be the truest love, which projects
<pb facs="tcp:170373:5"/> and works to the good of Souls. It is ſtrange, that men ſhould de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in the ſociety, and neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourhood of each other in this; and not deſire to meet, and live together, in Another world: That they ſhould ſtudy the Comfort, and Welfare of each other, in reſpect of their Perſons and Eſtates, and not beſtow a thought on their Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation.</p>
                  <p>Devout <hi>Bernard</hi> complain'd of old; <hi>Omnes amici, et omnes inimici: omnes neceſſarii, et omnes adverſarii; pax à pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganis, ſed non à filiis:</hi> and we are fallen into ſuch times. There is a generall pretence of amity, yet a generall emnity: we are all neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, yet all adverſaries; we have peace with the heathen, and we Christians differ among our
<pb facs="tcp:170373:6"/> ſelves: Our diviſions are the ſparks of that fire, which our bleſſed Saviour came to kindle, namely about the purity and pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of Evangelicall doctrines and ordinances. We agree about the ſubſtance of divine worſhip, and conteſt about the circumſtances.</p>
                  <p>It is our ſinne, and our ſhame, that we out-doe the Jewes in our malice againſt Chriſt: They cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied his body, but kept his gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment whole: we teare both his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and his garment. We diſpute, and wrangle about thoſe reverend ſolemnities, wherewith the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian religion in all ages, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong all nations, hath bin appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>relled and adorned.</p>
                  <p>But we ſhould all ſit downe, and conſider, what St. <hi>James</hi> ſayes; The wrath of man worketh
<pb facs="tcp:170373:6"/> not the righteouſneſſe of God, <hi>Jam.</hi> 1. 20. When all's done, when all is written and ſpoken that can be, on either ſide; The work of righteouſneſſe must be minded and regarded. That's ſoul-work. That will be the buſineſſe of inqeuſt at the laſt day: The queſtion then will not be, Who hath bin the beſt Souldier, nor who the beſt Scholler, but who hath bin the best Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian.</p>
                  <p>Sir, Upon this meditation, I thought no argument more proper for ſuch a ſolemne Convention, than this of Righteouſneſſe. It is a doctrine of univerſall concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and ſince you were pleaſed to call me to preach theſe two Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, I conceived it the beſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion of a reall affection, to preſent them to You, as a teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony,
<pb facs="tcp:170373:7"/> that I am an hearty wiſher both of your preſent and future happineſſe: That as you have bin a man of Warre, ſo by the ſtudy and acqueſt of that righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe which is taught and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commended in theſe diſcourſes, your end may be Peace.</p>
                  <p>The ſecond encouragement was the Service of my Country: for which (though not my native) I have a great obſervance and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect. I came a poor ſtranger in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it, yet have received many, and great favours from ſome eminent members of it; and no ſmall ones, from the generality. Their candid cenſures, and acceptance of my weake labours in this kind, was not the leaſt motive to undertake this ſervice. And they are able to teſtifie for me, that ſo often as I
<pb facs="tcp:170373:7"/> have appear'd in it, my diſcourſe hath had a tendency this way, to inſtruct in ſome point of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſse, that, through the bleſſing of God upon his Ordinance, I might redeem the reputation of this County from an unhappy obloquie it lay under.</p>
                  <p>The Third Encouragement, which was the higheſt and the greateſt, was the Service of the Lord; whoſe honour and glory we ſhould all ſtudy and endeavour to promote and advance, and which we can do in no better, or more ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable way, than by ſpeaking and doing righteouſneſſe.</p>
                  <p>Sir, I humbly preſent theſe plain Diſcourſes to your, and my Countrie's; ſervice but more eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially I devote them to the Glory of our God, whoſe unprofitable
<pb facs="tcp:170373:8"/> ſervant I am, but deſire to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove.</p>
                  <p>And as I have caſt forth this holy ſeed of righteouſneſſe into the world, ſo I ſhall not ceaſe to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech the Lord to water it with the dew of his grace, that it may bring forth the wiſhed fruits of it: Peace and quietneſſe and aſſurance for ever.</p>
                  <p>This is the deſire, and ſhall be the prayer of</p>
                  <closer>
                     <salute>Sir,</salute>
                     <signed>Your affectionate Friend and Servant, MICH. THOMAS.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="sermon">
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:170373:8"/>
                  <head>A SERMON Preached at the Aſſizes holden at <hi>Bridgenorth</hi> for the County of <hi>Salop,</hi> in the year, 1657.</head>
                  <epigraph>
                     <bibl>
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>. Pſalm 58. verſe 1.</bibl>
                     <q>Doe ye indeed ſpeak righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, O Congregation? Doe ye judge uprightly, O ye ſonnes of men?</q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F we inquire into the Argument, or Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of this Pſalm, and gueſſe aright at that; It will give us ſome light, to the proper Applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Text. And I ſhall
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:170373:9"/> neither waſte the time, nor your patience in unneceſſary quotations, or comparing the opinions of Expoſitors. I ſhall preſent that conjecture which I humbly conceive the moſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable, and ſo proceed upon it.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Lorinus,</hi> who with great induſtry hath collected the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions of the Greek and La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine Fathers; And <hi>Marlorate,</hi> who, with the like diligence, hath ſummed up the Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the Divines of the Reformed Churches, do both agree in this, that this Pſalm was written by <hi>David,</hi> and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended as an admonition to all the Officers of Juſtice in the Court of <hi>Saul;</hi> that when <hi>Saul</hi> ſhall call them to Councell, and they ſhall be ſitting in
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:170373:9"/> Judgment upon Him; that they vvould ſpeak righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſſe, and judge uprightly; that they would not hearken to the malicious informations of his Enemies, nor forme their Judgements according to the humour or the Deſignes of <hi>Saul,</hi> whoſe Counſellours and Officers they were; but pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently, and equally to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der both his Cauſe, and his Converſation, and to give ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence accordingly.</p>
                  <p>And allowing this to be the Argument or Occaſion of the Pſalm (as truly it is groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded upon very fair probabili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties) you will eaſily perceive, that the Text, in the proper Application of it, will have an influence upon this Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:170373:10"/> and prove a word in ſeaſon, in reſpect of the occaſion of this ſolemn Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention.</p>
                  <p>We are met at this time in the Name and fear of God, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the work of Juſtice: the Perſons, and Cauſes of men, are to be weighed and examined; And as I cannot ſay that there are any <hi>Davids</hi> to be tryed at this Aſſizes, men of ſuch emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent Pietie and Integrity as He was: So I hope there are none of <hi>Saul's</hi> Officers here, neither Men of ſuch proſtitute and mercenary conſciences as they were: <hi>Omnia Dicta Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini, omnibus poſita ſunt,</hi> ſayes <hi>Tertullian.</hi> The words of God have a generall proſpect; and though they may ſeem a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:170373:10"/> Admonition to ſome few men, yet they intend a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall Inſtruction to all men who may be concerned in the like caſe. This Pſalm was written about a matter of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, and Judgement: and that is the buſineſſe wee are all met upon: And foraſmuch as the Adminiſtration of Juſtice in this Nation, is by the Prudence and Wiſedome of our fore-fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, caſt into that forme that in all judiciall proceedings there are many Parties; The ſentence upon any cauſe, iſſues not from the boſome of any Judge alone, ſeeing he is tyed up to Proofs and Allegations: So that the miſcarriage in the worke of Juſtice, may proceed from the corruption of thoſe
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:170373:11"/> parties which prepare a Cauſe for Sentence.</p>
                  <p>If the Counſellors ſhall be corrupt and Covetous, and by their flouriſhing Eloquence ſhall guild over a rotten Cauſe.</p>
                  <p>If the Witneſſes ſhall be falſe and malicious, and ſeek rather their private revenge, than Publick Juſtice.</p>
                  <p>If the Jury ſhall be pack'd and partiall, or inſtructed to ſweare according to the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate intereſt of a Friend or a Landlord; there may prove ſad obſtructions in the vvork of Juſtice: this (as the Prophet <hi>Amos</hi> ſpeaks) may turn judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment into gall, and the fruit of righteouſneſſe into hem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lock.</p>
                  <p>And therefore I ſhall not
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:170373:11"/> addreſſe my diſcourſe to any particular Party, or Officer, in this great work of Juſtice; but to all, who are in any reſpect concerned in it, and enforce Holy <hi>David</hi>'s admonition in the Text, That they would ſpeak righteouſneſſe, and judge uprightly in all cauſes, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween all parties: that ſo Wickedneſſe and Impiety may have its condign puniſhment; and Innocence, and Honeſty, their due protection and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward. And this is the deſign and project of the enſuing diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe; for which I humbly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat your Chriſtian patience and the Lord's aſſiſtance.</p>
                  <p>The Text, you ſee, is preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the form of a Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:170373:12"/> but it appears by the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>text, that it is ſuch a Queſtion, which (as Divines obſerve) hath <hi>vim Negationis;</hi> it implyes a denyal, like that of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> Doe we provoke the Lord to Jealouſie? are we ſtronger then He? No, wee are not. So here in the Text: Doe yee ſpeake righteouſneſſe? doe ye Judge Uprightly? No, ye do not: for, their conviction followes in the ſecond verſe; <hi>Yea, in heart yee worke wickedneſse, and weigh the violence of your hands in the earth.</hi> So that the Text becomes (as <hi>Muſculus</hi> hath it) an invective, or a reproofe of the iniquity and injuſtice of <hi>Saul's</hi> Officers, and Counſellours, that when according to that place and
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:170373:12"/> power which they had with <hi>Saul,</hi> they ſhould have defend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and protected Him as an innocent perſon; they on the contrary proſecuted, and ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenc'd him as a ſeditious con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiratour. And this reproofe is imbitter'd with terrible threatnings and imprecations, as we find in the body of the Pſalm. And theſe <hi>David,</hi> in the Spirit of propheſie, breathes out, and denounces againſt them, as knowing that the Lord in his due time would plead his Cauſe, and by the glorious effects of his Power and Juſtice would give men occaſion to ſay: <hi>Verily there is a Reward for the Righteous? Doubtleſſe, there is a God that judgeth in the earth.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:170373:13"/>
                  <p> It well became the majeſty of that Spirit by which <hi>David</hi> wrote, to convey his admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in that form, by way of reproof or invective: But it will become me, to obſerve a greater diſtance. And I humbly crave leave to preſent that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, which I conceive due to this Auditory, and Occaſion, by way of Exhortation. Let me exhort you (I ſay) <hi>juſtitiam loqui, &amp; recta judicare,</hi> to ſpeak righteouſneſſe, and to judge uprightly. And when I have opened the Duty to you, and ſhewn you what it is, and how it may be done; we ſhall find, in the other words of the Text, weight enough to preſs it by way of motive or conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration. And this I ſhall do
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:170373:13"/> (by Gods aſſiſtance,) with all reſpect to your Patience and Imployment.</p>
                  <p>For the Duty it ſelfe, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare unto you what Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, and Upright Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is; I ſhall not perplexe your attention with the vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety of definitions, and diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions which might be offer'd out of the School-men and Caſuiſts. In this firſt part, I in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend onely the edification of the common ſort of people, who now are, or hereafter may be concerned as parties in the Adminiſtration of Juſtice. To them I ſay this; Righteouſneſſe is a conſtant purpoſe and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution, of giving to every one their own.</p>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:170373:14"/>
                  <p> And you may very eaſily perceive how this Definition agrees with the Caſe in the Text. <hi>David</hi> complaines of the Corruption, and Iniquity of thoſe that were Judges in his cauſe. <hi>Doeg</hi> was a falſe wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and gave in a malicious in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation againſt him. <hi>Saul</hi> was too apt of himſelfe to believe it; and yet he wanted not ſome flattering Courtiers, ſome per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chance of his privy Councell, who blew the Fire, and by their evill ſuggeſtions, turn'd <hi>Sauls</hi> hatred and jealouſie into a flame; that <hi>David</hi> was a ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitious, diſcontented perſon; and the Crown would not ſit faſt upon his head, while <hi>David</hi> lived: and with this unrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous dealing, <hi>David</hi> charges them. Now,</p>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:170373:14"/>
                  <p> Had theſe men been endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the grace of Juſtice, and Righteouſneſſe; had they had a conſtant purpoſe and reſolution of giving to every one their owne, that is, their due, then they had given <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> that Character and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation which vvas due to him, namely this: That <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> was miſ-repreſented to <hi>Saul;</hi> that he had given large teſtimonyes of a peaceable and quiet Spirit; that he had ſpared the Life of <hi>Saul,</hi> when it was in his power twice to have ſlaine him: Thus they ſhould have ſpoken righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; and defended an inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent perſon: But they did not. They wrought wickedneſſe in their hearts, as <hi>David</hi> ſpeaks
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:170373:15"/> here; they complied with <hi>Saul's</hi> humour in his bloody intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and perſecutions againſt <hi>David;</hi> and did not care though he periſhed, ſo long as they might ſecure their owne perſons and fortunes.</p>
                  <p>But this caſe, this tryall of righteouſneſſe, doth not often happen, yet ſometimes it doth: And then, thoſe that are in power and authority in any State, cannot better improve their greatneſſe, than by coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenancing and ſupporting op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed Innocence. Holy <hi>Job</hi> in his own juſt vindication, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates this, as one evidence of his righteouſneſſe; I delivered the poor that cryed, and the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therleſſe, and him that had none to help him. The bleſſing
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:170373:15"/> of him that was ready to pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, came upon me; and I made the Widdows heart to ſing for joy. I brake the jaws of the Wicked, and pluckt the ſpoyle out of his teeth, Chap. 29.</p>
                  <p>Even the heathens by the light of nature, did diſcern this to be the duty of a Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate. <hi>Sudandum eſt his, qui Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtratum gerunt, pro communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus commodis,</hi> ſayes <hi>Cicero:</hi> Such as undertake the office of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtracy, muſt ſweat and lay out themſelves for the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon good, muſt endure ſtorms and emnityes, and conteſt; not only with unjuſt and audaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, but even with potent ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries, in the defence of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocence. And <hi>Seneca</hi> reports it
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:170373:16"/> in the commendation of <hi>Caeſar, Omnium domos illius vigilia defendit:</hi> He was a man of ſuch a publicke Spirit, that his watchfullneſſe defended all mens houſes; his labour and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtry ſecured all men in their eaſe, and pleaſures, and vocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. A precedent, not unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of the knowledge and imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of thoſe, who ſhine as Starrs of the firſt magnitude in the Orbe of Honour: and let them know, that they are then truly glorious, when their Goodneſſe ſends forth as bright a beame, as their Great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; when they uſe their power, as well to defend the oppreſſed, as to puniſh the tranſgreſſour.</p>
                  <p>But I muſt not reſtraine the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:170373:16"/> worke of righteouſneſs to this caſe only; the duty is of a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter latitude, and yet St. <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stine</hi> in his Enarration of this fifty eighth Pſalme, hath redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced that great variety of caſes, to that one Head which our bleſſed Saviour in his Sermon layes down before us: <hi>What<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever yee would that men ſhould doe unto you, even ſo doe ye unto them.</hi> This is the grand rule of Equity. He that obſerves this rule, ſhall thinke and ſpeak, and do righteouſly, and be of an holy and blame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe converſation: This (ſayes that Father) was the firſt law which God wrote in the heart of Mankind. In matters of civill righteouſneſſe and mora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, in all thoſe dutyes which
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:170373:17"/> we owe to our Neighbour, a man need but knock at his own heart, and ask, What ſhall I do in ſuch or ſuch a tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion? and he ſhall hear this anſwer Ecchoing and ſound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thence: Do as thou would'ſt be done by.</p>
                  <p>Would'ſt thou, not have thy Children, or thy Servants diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedient or undutifull to thee? <hi>Honour thy Parents.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Would'ſt thou prolong thy Life to a good old Age? <hi>Do no Murder.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Would'ſt thou have thine owne Marriage-bed honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and undefiled? <hi>Do not commit Adultery.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Wouldſt thou poſſeſſe thy goods and eſtate in peace and ſafety? <hi>Do not Steal.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:170373:17"/>
                  <p> Would'ſt thou not be over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born in thy righteous cauſe by indirect proceedings? <hi>Do not bear falſe witneſſe againſt thy neighbour.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Would'ſt thou enjoy thy own houſe, and vvife, and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, and cattle, entire and without dammage to thy ſelf? <hi>Covet nothing of thy Neighbours:</hi> Do as thou wouldſt be done by.</p>
                  <p>This rule (ſayes St <hi>Hierom)</hi> is <hi>Compendioſum commonitori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um. A breviate</hi> of the whole duty of man to his neighbour: If he would neither do evill to, nor ſuffer evill from, his neighbour; let him remember This. <hi>Lorinus</hi> tells us, and <hi>Beza</hi> affirmes as much, that, in ſome Antient Greek Copyes,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:170373:18"/> This rule of our bleſſed Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our was inſerted by the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles into their canons, in their firſt Councell at Antioch. Having decreed, that they ſhould abſtaine from meats offered to Idolls, and from bloud, and from things ſtrang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, and from fornication, then it was added: <hi>And what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever yee would that men ſhould doe unto you, doe ſo unto them.</hi> As if this were the moſt perfect rule for a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an to walk by.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Lampridius</hi> tells us alſo, that the Emperour <hi>Alexander Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verus,</hi> did ſo highly prize this Rule, that He cauſed it to be written in his Palace, and in many publike places; and that in his Military diſcipline,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:170373:18"/> he was wont to puniſh his Souldiers in this manner; If upon their march they had plundered any thing, and were taken with it, they were brought back to the owner, and there in his fight and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence were beaten either with clubs, or with rods; and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brayded in this manner. Would you be content that that ſhould have been done to you, which you have done to him? You have robbed and ſpoyled this man of his goods would you be robbed and ſpoyl'd of your own? And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thus upbrayded for tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſing this evident law of nature, he was diſmiſſ'd with ſhame and ſorrow.</p>
                  <p>And (my Chriſtian Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren)
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:170373:19"/> let us all with ſhame and ſorrow, conſider our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linquency in this caſe, How contrary we have walked to this rule of Equity; either in an utter contempt, or forgetfull<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of it. How many poore Soules are there now in the Jayle, and to be tryed for their lives, who with a deep ſorrow and remorſe of conſcience wiſh they had alwayes walked according to this rule. Such as are to be arraigned for Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, or Felony, how paſſionate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly do they wiſh, they could gather up that bloud which they have ſpilt, and that they had kept their hands cleer from all acts of Violence and Robbery. But alaſs, it is too late, and 'tis to be feared that
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:170373:19"/> ſome of them muſt yield up their lives, to ſatisfie thoſe righteous and equall lawes, which they have tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed.</p>
                  <p>And although our piety and our prayers are in a great mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure due to Them, let us not forget Our ſelves. Let us look into, and examine our owne hearts, whether we ſtand not guilty before the Judge of all the World of many acts of unrighteouſneſſe. Alaſs, it is but little, that our finns, are not written on our foreheads as theirs are; that they are not legible to the World in a pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like inditement. The time will come, when we ſhall be ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign'd in the Court of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, and groan under the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:170373:20"/> gnawings of that greedy worm, which nothing can ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie but a broken heart. Oh (my Bretheren) lets think up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it. We know not how neer the day of the Lord, is. 'Tis 1600 years ago and upward, ſince St. <hi>James</hi> told us: <hi>The judge ſtandeth at the doore.</hi> 'Tis his infinite patience and long-ſuffering; that he doth not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into Judgement with us. 'Twere wiſe and ſafe, by a ſpeedy and unfeigned repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance to prepare to meet Him, and by faith to get on the Breſt-plate of Righteouſneſſe, by which only we ſhall be able to ſtand in that evill day.</p>
                  <p>But although we muſt make mention of the righteouſneſſe of CHRIST onely, in the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:170373:20"/> point of juſtification, yet there is a ſtock of morall righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe we muſt lay in too, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare the truth and life of our faith, of which we have a preg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant intimation in the Text. And having ſhewn you the <hi>Quid,</hi> what this duty is that <hi>David</hi> enquires after: It fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes now that I ſhew you the <hi>Quomodo,</hi> How it is to be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed; which appeares in the words of the queſtion, <hi>Do ye indeed ſpeak righteouſneſs? do ye judge uprightly?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I ſhall obſerve in this part but two branches; for we may well conceive, that thoſe phra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, Speaking righteouſneſſe, and judging uprightly; are but Synonyma, important of the ſame thing, and under that
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:170373:21"/> joynt-notion, I ſhall conſider them.</p>
                  <p>And then a ſecond thing will be: This ſpeaking righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe (indeed); we ſhall per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive ſome weight in that word, when I come to open it.</p>
                  <p>For the firſt of theſe: How are we to ſpeak righteouſneſs, or to judge uprightly?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Mollerus</hi> tells, that ſome Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitours render the words thus; <hi>An certè mutam juſtitiam loquimini?</hi> It ſeemes to be an improper ſpeech: but they thus explaine it, that <hi>David</hi> charges the counſellours of <hi>Saul</hi> with an unjuſt ſilence. Do ye ſpeak righteouſneſſe? that is, Ye do not ſpeak righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe: ye do not declare that innocence and integrity,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:170373:21"/> which in your owne conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces ye believe to be in me.</p>
                  <p>I touch'd upon this before, and ſhewed you, what reflecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it might have upon the great Officers and Counſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours of State; let me in a word or two bring it a little lower.</p>
                  <p>As it may be a fault in a Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to depoſe more then the truth; ſo it may be a fault to conceal any materiall circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, which may make for the diſcovery of the truth. They had a proverb among the Antients, when a man would not ſpeak freely what he thought or knew in any cauſe, they would ſay: <hi>Bovem habet in lingua:</hi> He hath a bull in his tongue; the Atnenian money having the figure of a Bull,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:170373:22"/> ſtamp'd upon it: and by that proverb they would taxe him with bribery, that he had ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken money to hold his peace. And the like ſcoff was put up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Demoſthenes,</hi> when, upon a gift received he would not plead, as he did againſt the Meleſian Embaſſadours: <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, He had ſwallowed a bribe, and that made his throat ſore: I have heard complaints in this kind. Poor men, when with great coſt and trouble, they have prepared their Cauſe for a hearing, have yet loſt it; their witneſſes have bin cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted to ſay leſſe then they knew; and their Counſell ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken off to attend other cauſes in other Courts; and ſo all hath miſcarried for not ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:170373:22"/> righteouſneſſe: unrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe hath prevailed againſt him. But ile carry this note no further.</p>
                  <p>Let me now take up that terme in the Text (indeed), and weigh it to you, and you may receive ſome farther light and inſtruction from it. The Lxx render it, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, that is, Do ye <hi>truly</hi> ſpeak righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe? <hi>Apollinarius</hi> thus: <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>; that is, do ye un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dauntedly ſpeak righteouſneſs? So now we may gueſſe at holy <hi>Davids</hi> meaning. Do ye ſpeak righteouſneſſe without feare, without favour, from the truth and ſincerity of your hearts?</p>
                  <p>And now that I have clear'd the words, let all the Officers and Miniſters of Juſtice from
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:170373:23"/> the higheſt to the loweſt, be pleaſed to ſuffer a word of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation.</p>
                  <p>There is no one thing, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion onely excepted, that more ſecureth and adorneth a State then juſtice doth; It is both <hi>Columna &amp; Corona Rei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pub:</hi> A prop to make it ſubſiſt firme in it ſelfe, and a crown to make it glorious in the eyes of others. <hi>Jus et Aequitas vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cula Civitatum,</hi> ſaies <hi>Cicero;</hi> As the Cement is to the Building: ſo is Juſtice to the Body-poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick; it holds all together. Bodies politick owe both their ſtrength, and their height to Juſtice. So <hi>Solomon</hi> tells us: Righteouſneſs eſtabliſheth the Throne, and exalteth the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:170373:23"/>
                  <p> It was the Lords command to the officers of juſtice in the 16 of <hi>Deuter: That which is altogether juſt ſhalt thou follow. Juſtiſſimam Juſtitiam ſectare, Tremelius</hi> renders it: The old Vulgar, <hi>Juſtum juſtè perſequere.</hi> According to the originall, we ſhould read it, <hi>Juſtice Juſtice ſhalt thou follow.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The Charge you ſee from the great Law-giver, is very ſtrict, preſſing all his under-officers to the execution of Juſtice. We of this Nation are happy in an excellent body of Lawes, and we want but one Law more, to enforce Magiſtrates to the execution of thoſe Lawes. Execution in Polity, is like Elocution in Oratory. <hi>Primum, Secundum, Tertium:</hi>
                     <pb n="32" facs="tcp:170373:24"/> The prime, and the maine, the all in all of it.</p>
                  <p>The Lord by his Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> commands, <hi>Keep ye judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and execute Juſtice.</hi> Now it were a ſad thing if we ſhould <hi>keep judgment</hi> as a Priſoner, or <hi>execute</hi> it as a Malefactour. The Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> complain'd of ſome ſuch, that did with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the truth in unrighteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: but God forbid there ſhould be any ſuch found a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us, who by any baſe arts ſhould obſtruct the courſe of judgment, or award a pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment to any one, who hath walked according to antient and known Lawes.</p>
                  <p>The purpoſe of the Lord by his Prophet was this: <hi>keep Judgment:</hi> that is, declare it,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:170373:24"/> lay open the Law in the grounds and reaſons of it, and execute juſtice, that is, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſter it impartially, indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferently, and without reſpect of perſons. The Jewes had a proverb; Tranſgreſſours need a Seſſions houſe.</p>
                  <p>It is not enough that good Lawes are enacted by pious Princes and their Councell.</p>
                  <p>It is not enough that they are rightly underſtood by the Reverend and learned Judges.</p>
                  <p>Nor enough, that they are diligently enquired into by the Grand or petty Juries.</p>
                  <p>The maine thing, is, the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution of the Lawes, that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſneſſe ſhould not dare to out-face Juſtice, that the Magiſtrate do not withhold
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:170373:25"/> his hand from ſeizing upon im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudent iniquity. Remember the importance of this word in the Text <hi>[Indeed]:</hi> that ye ſpeake and doe righteouſneſſe <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>truly,</hi> without any by, or baſe reſpects, and <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out fear or care.</p>
                  <p>Self-reſpects are too often obſtructions in the courſe of Juſtice. <hi>Viderit Utilitas,</hi> is no good motto for a Magiſtrate. Favour may blear his eyes, but gifts will blind them: He that is <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> will eaſily be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, and that undoes all. Conſider the caſe in the Text, between <hi>SAUL</hi> and <hi>DAVID,</hi> and you will wonder the leſſe at the Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption of his Officers, when you hear the argument he ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:170373:25"/> to them. He had intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence that his Son <hi>Jonathan</hi> was in league with <hi>David,</hi> and, ſuſpecting the revolt of other great Officers, he ſpeaks thus to them: Hear now ye <hi>Benja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mites:</hi> Will <hi>David</hi> give every one of you Fields and Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yards, and make you Captains of thouſands, and Captains of hundreds? 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 22. 7. Here was an hook cunningly bai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, to draw them to his own party; and it is hard to ſay, in whom the Corruption was greater: In <hi>Saul</hi> to offer, or in his Officers to accept? in Him to ſuggeſt a temptation, or in them to yeeld to it; but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween both, we know that <hi>David</hi> a man after Gods owne heart, was purſued and perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted.
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:170373:26"/> So <hi>David</hi> tells <hi>Saul:</hi> I have not ſinned againſt thee, yet thou hunteſt my Soul to take it, 1 <hi>Samuel.</hi> 24. 11.</p>
                  <p>I perſwade my ſelfe, you ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver readd the Hiſtory of <hi>David</hi> but it begat ſad thoughts in you, that a man ſo innocent, ſhould be ſo violently proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted: but ſee, what ſelf reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pects will doe, when once a man layes-by all care of piety and religion, and deſignes no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but the advancement of his own private intereſt, Hee cannot ſay at what ſinne he will ſtop. It is a great truth that of <hi>Solomon,</hi> Hee that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiveth gifts over-throweth a land.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Vir Oblationum</hi> according to
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:170373:26"/> the Original, A man that is rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to receive any motion that ſhall be offer'd him, if it come with a gift; A man that comes to an Aſſizes, as <hi>Plutarch</hi> ſaid of <hi>Stratocles, tanquam ad meſsem auream</hi> as to a golden Harveſt, and brings a mercenary tongue and conſcience with him; what man though never ſo innocent can be ſecure of his life or for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune? VVhen <hi>Judas</hi> opened his heart to the High Prieſt with that indication <hi>Quid da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitis?</hi> What will ye give me? They knew they had an agent for their turne. He betrayes his Maſter, and ſells his bloud, though he knew it was inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent.</p>
                  <p>That moſt Chriſtian duty of Selfe-denyall, runnes through
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:170373:27"/> all the offices of a mans life. It is the greateſt preſerver of Peace and Unity, and righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe: He that hath learnt to deny Himſelfe, will never envy the happineſſe of his neighbour; much leſſe invade his rights or poſſeſſions, and with a violent hand ſeize up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them. He hath learnt with St. <hi>Paul,</hi> in whatſoever ſtate he is, therewith to be content; and to ſuch as are in a better condition then him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, he can ſay, The bleſſing of the Lord be upon you: I bleſſe you in the name of the LORD.</p>
                  <p>Againe to ſpeak Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe truely, is to ſpeak it with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out favour. Favour in a Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate, when miſdemeanours
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:170373:27"/> are groſſe and palpable, is the nurſe of Vice. St. <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> calls it, the mother of all ſin. It is not ſeldome ſeene, that when a man hath ſpent his youth, and his ſtrength in the ſervice of ſome great One, he is at length rewarded with a Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence to hang up a Signe: and that proves perchance a Sign of drunkenneſſe, a ſign of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thriftyneſſe, a ſign of wanton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, a ſign of prophanneſſe, and all kind of wickedneſs. The Spirits of Godly men are vex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, to ſee ſuch a confluence of all ſorts to that Sign of ſinne: and they doe not only grieve that that houſe of ſinne is ſometimes as full as the houſe of God, but complaine of it; yet that Sign muſt not be
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:170373:28"/> pull'd down: Why? He was my old Servant, and I muſt winke at him. And this favour hath an evill influence upon his fellow Commiſſioners: If he will winke, they muſt not ſee. They muſt ſhew favour to his Servant, that their owne may find the like.</p>
                  <p>But what will be the end of this? He that will winke at the treſpaſs of the Lawes in his ſervant, how pore-blind would he be toward a Friend, or a Kinſman? Yea, ſtarke blinde, if a Sonne ſhould be a treſpaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer.</p>
                  <p>Such was the Juſtice of the Heathens that they did not ſtumble at greater ſtones then theſe. <hi>Torquatus</hi> a Romane, and <hi>Zaleucus</hi> a Grecian, ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:170373:28"/> not to give ſentence even upon their own Sonnes. You know the old word, <hi>Amicus Plato &amp;c. Sed magis amica Veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas.</hi> Truth and Righteouſneſſe ſhould be dearer to us then all the World beſide; We may have a fair reſpect for ſervants, and friends, and kindred, and Children: but the peace of our Country, and the honour of Religion, and the glory of God ſhould over-weigh all. Let the Chriſtian Magiſtrate hear the Heathen Oratour <hi>Exuat perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam Judicis, qui induit Amici.</hi> The affection of a friend fits not the function of a magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate. He may ſay to his Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance, In all matters of civility I am yours, but in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Juſtice I am God's, and
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:170373:29"/> my Country's ſervant.</p>
                  <p>Let me note but one thing more in this part, If yee would ſpeake Righteouſneſſe indeed, ſpeake it according to <hi>Apolli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narius Metaphraſe</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>: with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out feare. It was fear, no doubt that made <hi>Saul's</hi> Officers ſo corrupt as they were. When ſelfe-intereſt brought them to ſerve him in his unrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous deſignes, ſelfe-preſervation continued them in his ſervice: Their worldly wiſedome made them conſider that, He that could give them fields and vineyards, and thoſe great commands, could as eaſily take them away. And ſuch as yeeld themſelves ſervants unto ſinne for gaine; 'tis ſome queſtion, whether they would yeeld
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:170373:29"/> themſelves ſervants unto righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, upon apparant diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>advantage. The Kingdome of <hi>Iſrael</hi> was in a ſad ſtate; when <hi>Naboth</hi> muſt dye, rather than <hi>Jeſabel</hi> be diſpleaſed: and <hi>Chriſt</hi> muſt be Crucified, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than <hi>Pilate</hi> offend <hi>Caeſar.</hi> And it will grow as ſad with us, if the portion of the Wid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow, and the Fatherleſs may be ſwallowed up; and neither Witneſs, nor Jury-man dare ſpeake his Conſcience, for feare of the mighty Oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſour.</p>
                  <p>'Twas a noble courage in thoſe Antient Biſhops, who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing charged by the <hi>Arrian</hi> Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour, to condemne <hi>Athanaſius</hi> without witneſs, and unheard, onely <hi>propter Me,</hi> on the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour's
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:170373:30"/> word, refuſed to do it; and would rather hazzard their eſtates, then do ſuch an act of unjuſtice. And let the feare of the Lord ſo rule in all our hearts as not to feare the faces or frownes of men, by them to be over-awed or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded to any act whereby the Glory of Chriſt, or his Goſpel may be diſparaged; or the right of our neighbour in any mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure diminiſhed.</p>
                  <p>And now that I have ſhewn you What Righteouſneſs is, and how yee may ſpeake it <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed,</hi> Let me begg but two minutes more of your Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an patience for thoſe two Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives or Conſiderations in the Text, that may preſs you to them; and I have done.</p>
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:170373:30"/>
                  <p> And theſe Motives will riſe out of the Text, like a Party laid in ambuſh, and ſurprize your Spirits, while you thinke not of them.</p>
                  <p>There are two motives to ſpeake righteouſneſs, in thoſe two Compellations, with which <hi>David</hi> beſpeaks theſe Officers of <hi>Saul.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>O yee Congregation! O yee Sons of Men! Calvin</hi> conceives that <hi>David</hi> expreſses himſelf thus by way of contempt. q. d: O yee ſervants of <hi>Saul!</hi> albeit when ye are met in Councell, ye ſeem to be a Congregation, ſuch a number of men, whoſe power and policy, I, a poor fugitive, am not able to reſiſt; yet know, that yee are but the Sonnes of
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:170373:31"/> men. Ye, by your Counſels, ſeek to take away my life, and when ye have taken it, ye are but the Sons of men, Ye muſt dye your ſelves. <hi>Man that is born of a Woman</hi> (ſayes <hi>Job) is but of few dayes.</hi> The greater ſhould our care be to ſpend them well. And I ſuppoſe that learned man, took the ground of this gloſs from the ſignification of the originall terme, <hi>Elem:</hi> which ſignifies <hi>Manipulus ſpicarum,</hi> a ſheaffe of Straw or a bundle of Reeds: and in that ſenſe it is found in the thirty ſeventh of <hi>Geneſis,</hi> verſe ſeventh, Where <hi>Joſeph</hi> relating his dream, tells his brethren: that their ſheaves bowed to his ſheafe. There's the word <hi>Elem.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:170373:31"/>
                  <p> And now you may perceive the weight of this Motive. That a Congregation of men, conſpiring in an act of unrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, are but a ſheafe of ſtraw, and a ſheafe of ſtraw is nothing in the hand of God. God is a conſuming fire, ſayes the <hi>Apoſtle:</hi> and when <hi>God ſhall come in flaming fire to render ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance to thoſe who obey not the Goſpell of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> what will become of this ſheafe of ſtraw?</p>
                  <p>And it is conſiderable to this purpoſe, what <hi>David</hi> ſpeaks in the 82 <hi>Pſalm, God ſtandeth in the Congregation of the mighty,</hi> He judgeth among the Gods, verſ. 1.</p>
                  <p>Magiſtrates are called Gods, becauſe they are advanced to
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:170373:32"/> do the work of God, for ſuch is the work of Juſtice. And ſo <hi>Hezekiah</hi> told his Judges; See what ye do, For ye execute not the judgment of men, but of God.</p>
                  <p>Well, but yet God ſtands in their Congregation. He is preſent at their Counſells, and He judges among them. He ſees, and knowes all their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes, how they are laid, and how they muſt be carried on: and then, as it is in the ſecond <hi>Pſalm, When the Rulers took Counſell againſt the Lord and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his annointed,</hi> The Lord ſat in Heaven and laughed at them, and had them in deriſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. But be pleaſed to reflect upon this paſſage in this 82. <hi>Pſalm, God ſtandeth in the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation</hi>
                     <pb n="49" facs="tcp:170373:32"/> 
                     <hi>of the Mighty.</hi> The meaning is, as I ſaid, He is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent. It is not enough that He looks down from Heaven, and ſees all Congregations afarre off, but he comes, and ſtands in them. And ſome Expoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors conceive, that God is preſented in that poſture of ſtanding, to denote His atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. As you know it is with us, when we ſit and heare a diſcourſe, which we would liſten better to, we ſtand up. And ſo here. God is ſaid to ſtand: that is, he is ſo preſent, as that alſo he is attentive. Nothing paſſes but <hi>Deo aſtante, &amp; atteſtante,</hi> He is an eare-wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and an eye-witneſs, yea and an heart-witneſſe of all that is ſaid, or thought, or
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:170373:33"/> done in any Congregation.</p>
                  <p>And this notion <hi>David</hi> did conceive very proper to inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>midate the hearts of his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, to re-mind them, that God ſtands in their Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that He is preſent at all their meetings, and attentive to all their debates: that they are but a ſheafe of ſtraw, he can break their band, and ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter them as the chaffe before the wind. And that is the firſt motive to incline us to ſpeak righteouſly.</p>
                  <p>And the ſecond is this. <hi>Let us conſider that we are but the ſonnes of Men.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And upon this theme, Holy <hi>David</hi> in another Pſalm, prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches to us a Lecture of Morta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity. Surely (ſayes He) every
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:170373:33"/> man living is altogether vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. In the 62 <hi>Pſalm,</hi> He wraps up all mankind in that ſheet of corruption: <hi>Men of low de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree are vanity.</hi> True: there's but little doubt or diſpute of that: but what are men of an high degree? <hi>They are a lye.</hi> That is: There is no ſafe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pending on them, their breath is in their noſtrills as well as other mens, and dye they muſt; and dye they may, aſſoon as o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. So that, take the whole race of mankind together; High and low, Rich and poor, the meane and the Mighty, and lay them upon a ballance, and they are altogether lighter then vanity. And this was that which <hi>David</hi> intended in that 82 <hi>Pſalm,</hi> when he ſaid, <hi>He</hi>
                     <pb n="52" facs="tcp:170373:34"/> 
                     <hi>judgeth among the gods.</hi> If God did onely ſtand in the Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations of unrighteous men, and heard, and would do no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, the care were the leſs; yea (but ſaies <hi>David</hi> here,) He ſtands to judge.</p>
                  <p>It is acutely obſerved by a late reverend Author; that God's <hi>ſtanding</hi> in the firſt verſ. hath reference to the fall of thoſe mighty ones in the ſixth and ſeventh verſes. I have ſaid ye are Gods, and all children of the moſt high, but ye ſhall dye like men, and <hi>fall</hi> like one of the Princes. God is a ſtanding God; He onely doth and will ſtand, when all unrighteous men, how great ſoever ſhall fall, and fall to duſt. Their greatneſs cannot exempt them
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:170373:34"/> from the firſt ſtatute, <hi>Statutum eſt omnibus ſemel mori,</hi> It is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed for all men once to dye; Nor from the ſecond ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute; <hi>et poſt mortem Judicium,</hi> and after death to come to Judgment.</p>
                  <p>Magiſtrates, though they are called Gods, yet they are <hi>Dii ſub Judice;</hi> when they have judged others, they muſt be judged themſelves. They are <hi>Dii caduci, &amp; Dii judicandi:</hi> Gods that ſhall fall, and Gods that muſt come to Judgment.</p>
                  <p>Now then for the Conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of all. Let me recommend this one Meditation to you. I may call it an occaſionall Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation, becauſe you may have frequent occaſions to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber you of it. You know a
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:170373:35"/> ſheafe of Corne when it is in the band, will ſtand by it ſelfe, and endure an indifferent blaſt of wind, ere it fall: but, undoe the band, and you cannot make a ſingle ſtraw to ſtand. I inferre this.</p>
                  <p>When unrighteous men aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble, and ſit in Counſell to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, then they are as a ſheafe in the band: their ſtrength may be conſiderable and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>midable, and the upright man may be over-born in Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. A pack<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>d jury (as I ſaid before,) and a few ſuborned witneſſes, may carry any cauſe; and it lies not in the power of the moſt prudent upright Judge, to prevent it. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as when the band is once bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, (as God will break ſuch
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:170373:35"/> bands), when ſuch men return to their ſingle capacities, their weakeneſſe will not onely be viſible but deſpicable. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though conſidered in their united capacities, in their grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt ſtrength, compared with God, they are but as a ſheafe of ſtraw laid upon a flaming fire, which leaves onely the poor revenge of its aſhes to hide the embers of that fire which conſum'd it. Yet it pleaſes God ſometimes to break the band, and to ſingle thoſe unrighteous men out, and in their ſolitude to purſue them with horrour of Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and the diſtracting re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of their perjuries and forgeries, their frivolous delayes, and demurres, their
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:170373:36"/> frauds and ſubornations, and thoſe irreparable injuries they have done; and they ſhall be no more able to ſtand, and look either God or good men in the face, than a ſingle ſtraw is to reſiſt a whirlewind.</p>
                  <p>I ſhall ſhew you this in one example. <hi>Doeg</hi> the Edomite was an inſtrument of much e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill to <hi>David,</hi> and to all that favour'd his righteous cauſe; by his malicious information, <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bimelech</hi> the Prieſt and eighty four more of the Prieſts of the Lord were put to the Sword. What became of him? <hi>Lori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> tells us out of <hi>Rabbi Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,</hi> that it was a received tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition among the Jewes, that he and his only Sonne dyed in this manner: That <hi>Doeg</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:170373:36"/> was armour-bearer to <hi>Saul</hi> in that battle with the Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſtines, at which he dyed. There, when <hi>Saul</hi> had fallen upon his own Sword, and ſlain himſelfe; <hi>Doeg</hi> calls his Son, and ſends him with <hi>Saul's</hi> Crown and bracelet to <hi>David,</hi> thinking thereby to engrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate himſelfe; and then <hi>Doeg</hi> falls upon his owne Sword, as <hi>Saul</hi> had done, and kills him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe; and his Son inſtead of a reward from <hi>David,</hi> is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to be ſlain. And there was an end of <hi>Saul,</hi> and <hi>Doeg</hi> his informer, and their family.</p>
                  <p>The Lord by that army of the Philiſtines brake up the Congregation, and made them know they were but the Sons of men, and that they were not
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:170373:37"/> able to ſtand, when he came to judge them.</p>
                  <p>Now the Lord help us to conſider of theſe things and diſpoſe our hearts to love the work of righteouſneſſe, and in all our dealings with men to behave our ſelves juſtly and uprightly, that when we ſhall come to dye like men, we may finde the fruit of righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, which is peace: even Peace with God, and peace with our owne conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, that we may commend our ſpirits into the hands of the God of our righteouſneſs, with joy and not with fear.</p>
                  <div type="prayer">
                     <pb n="59" facs="tcp:170373:37"/>
                     <head>The Prayer after Sermon.</head>
                     <p>GReat and Glorious Lord God, who art righteous in all thy wayes, and holy in all thy works: be good and gracious unto us thy poor Creatures, who here stand guilt, before thee of many acts of unrighteouſneſſe, for having re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected and deſpiſed thy moſt pure and holy lawes, and have choſen rather to walke after the luſts and imaginations of our owne hearts.</p>
                     <p>We have defaced that perfect Image of righteouſneſſe and Holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, in which we were created, we have defiled our ſelves with the pollutions of ſinne; ſo that all our righteouſneſſe is but as a fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy ragge, and we cannot but loath and abhorre our ſelves for all our abhominations.</p>
                     <p>Bleſſed God, we deſire to return
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:170373:38"/> unto Thee, and to ſeek thy face; not only for thy mercy and pardon for the ſins we have co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted, but for thy Spirit and thy grace, that we may be renewed &amp; reſtored to that ſtate of holines whence we are faln.</p>
                     <p>And foraſmuch as the Miniſtry of thy Word is the means which thou haſt ordained, &amp; promiſed to ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifie to that end; We humbly call upon thee for a bleſſing upon that portion of thy Word which hath bin diſpenſed unto us at this time.</p>
                     <p>Great God! our hearts are in thy hand, we beſeech Thee mould and faſhion them according to thine own holy will. Beget in us a conſtant purpoſe and reſolution of giving to every one their owne, and re-imprint in our hearts that excellent rule of righteouſneſſe, Not to do any thing to our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:170373:38"/> which we would not be content that he ſhould doe to us.</p>
                     <p>We are met at this time, O Lord, about thine own worke, The Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of Juſtice and Judgement; we beſeech thee aſſiſt us in it. As we begin this worke in thy Name, give us grace to continue in it in thy Fear.</p>
                     <p>Touch the hearts of all thoſe who are in any reſpects intereſted as parties in the adminiſtration of Juſtice, that they may all ſpeak righteouſneſse and judge upright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, without reſpect to themſelves or reſpect to their friends, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out feare of the face of any man</p>
                     <p>And give us all grace to conſider that a congregation of men, conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring in an act of unrighteouſneſse, are but as a ſheafe of ſtraw, not able to conteſt with thee who art a
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:170373:39"/> conſuming fire. Oh help us to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, that how great or mighty ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever we be in this World, we are yet but the ſonnes of men, fraile and mortall, and know not how ſoon we may be called to thy Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment Seat: And let theſe medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions quicken us to an holy care to prepare our accounts, and to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>have ourſelves ſo righteouſly to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward all men here on earth, as that we may cheerefully commend our Spirits to the God of Heaven.</p>
                     <p>Hear us O God, and anſwer us according to thy wonted grace &amp; goodneſſe; ſupply all our defects out of the fullneſſe of Chriſt Jeſus, who is the Lord our Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: to whom with thee, O Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and thy bleſſed Spirit, we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to aſcribe all honour and pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and prayſe, now and for ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more. <hi>Amen, Amen.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:170373:39"/>
                  <p> A SERMON, Preached at the ASSIZES Held at BRIDGNORTH For the County of <hi>Salop</hi> in the year, 1657.</p>
                  <p>On the Lord's Day.</p>
                  <p>By <hi>Mich: Thomas,</hi> Rector of <hi>Sockton</hi> in the ſame COUNTY.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Humphrey Moſeley</hi> at the <hi>Prince</hi>'s <hi>Armes</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-yard. 1659.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:170373:40"/>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="sermon">
                  <pb n="63" facs="tcp:170373:40"/>
                  <epigraph>
                     <bibl>
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>. Pſalme 37. verſe 37.</bibl>
                     <q>Mark the perfect man, and behold the upright: For the end of that man is peace.</q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T may perchance raiſe your attention to the Doctrine of this Text, when you ſhall conſider, that it is a branch of that Pſalme, which hath alwayes bin in very high eſteem both among the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tients, and our Moderne Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines.</p>
                  <p>Origen calls it <hi>Humanae ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mae Medicinam.</hi> It is Phyſick for the ſoul of man, foraſmuch as
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:170373:41"/> it reproves ſinne, and teaches us to live according to the lawes of God.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Athanaſius</hi> recommends it to be readd by all thoſe who are ſcandalized at the proſperity of the wicked, and find them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves tempted to go along with them in their wayes; and to think this world to be go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verned by chance or fortune, that God is not a God of Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; that he makes no dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference between the righteous and the wicked.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Calvin</hi> and <hi>Mollerus</hi> meet both in this cenſure of it, that it containes <hi>doctrinam apprimè utilem,</hi> exceeding profitable doctrine; and <hi>Lorinus</hi> tells us, that <hi>Fulgentius</hi> (that great light of the Church in <hi>Africa,)</hi>
                     <pb n="65" facs="tcp:170373:41"/> by reading St. <hi>Augustines</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentary upon it, was conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by it.</p>
                  <p>The tree then being ſo good, you may fairely preſume the Text, which is a branch of it, may yield you the like fruit. I may not unfitly call the Text, <hi>Totius Pſalmi</hi> Epitomen. The ſummary or abridgement of the whole Pſalm. The doct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine which is diſperſed in the other verſes of it, is collected and united in this.</p>
                  <p>All the defect will lye on my part, by reaſon of my weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, I ſhall not be able to ſhake this ſo full laden branch, that all the fruit of it may fall amongſt you. So farre as the Lord hath enabled me to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand the doctrine of it, I
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:170373:42"/> ſhall humbly preſent it to your religious conſideration, and ſhall hope, that that ſleight taſt of it, which you will receive at this time by my ſervice, will provoke your holy appetites to make a farther enquiry in your private meditations.</p>
                  <p>But not to waſte more, either of the time, or your patience, be pleaſed to take the Text divided into theſe three parts.</p>
                  <p>Here is an Act, and an Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject; and they are both two<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold.</p>
                  <p>The Act is, to Mark and to Behold.</p>
                  <p>The Object of this Act is the Perfect and the Upright man.</p>
                  <p>And in the third place here is the reaſon of the Act which
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:170373:42"/> is very weighty and conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; <hi>For the end of that man is Peace.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But I muſt crave leave to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert the order of theſe parts, and conſider the Object firſt, Who this perfect and upright man is. And then paſſe to the Act, what it is to Mark and to behold Him. To which act, we ſhall be the better diſpoſed, by the weight of the reaſon which enforces it; <hi>Mark the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect man, and behold the upright: For the end of that man is peace.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <div n="1" type="part">
                     <head>The firſt part: The Object.</head>
                     <p>I confeſſe, I find much varie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in the ſeverall Tranſlations concerning the reading of the Text. The <hi>LXX</hi> render it
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:170373:43"/> 
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, and according to the old vulgate, <hi>Custodi innocentiam, &amp; vide ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitatem:</hi> and then we ſhould read the Text, <hi>Keep inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency and take heed to the thing that is right.</hi> And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though <hi>Lorinus</hi> follow theſe tranſlations, yet we acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge that other grave Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors, <hi>Concretè interpretantur ex Hebraeo,</hi> render it out of the Hebrew by the Concrete. <hi>Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerva perfectum, &amp; aſpice rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum;</hi> and ſo <hi>Junius,</hi> and <hi>Treme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius</hi> have tranſlated it; and ſo alſo thoſe Divines of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Churches, whoſe opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions <hi>Marlorate</hi> hath collected. And truly the difference is not great, whether we read it in the Abſtract, or in the Concrete,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:170373:43"/> the one will be the Expoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the other: and ſo the perfect man will be, He that keepeth innocency; and the Upright man, He that ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth heed to the thing that is right.</p>
                     <p>But we muſt behold this Object at a neerer diſtance; and let us look upon this per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection and uprightneſſe in the Root, and in the Branches of it; and then, according to our Engliſh word, we ſhall have three Marks by which we may know who this perfect and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right man is; and ſo the better judge of our ſelves, whether we are ſuch or no.</p>
                     <p>The Root of this Perfection and Uprightneſſe, I place in the Heart; and the branches of it,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:170373:44"/> in the Words and Actions of men. And this method anſwers that Diſtinction ſo common a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong Divines; <hi>Integritas Cordis, Oris, Operis:</hi> The Uprightneſſe of the Heart, of the Mouth, and of the Hand; and upon the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of theſe Marks, we ſhall have the fuller and the cleerer proſpect of Him.</p>
                     <p>And I was put into this me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod, not ſo much by the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon diſtinction, as by the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priety of the termes in the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginal. We read of <hi>Noah,</hi> that he was a perfect man, <hi>Gen.</hi> 6. 9. of <hi>Jacob,</hi> that he was a plain man, <hi>Gen.</hi> 25. 27. of <hi>Job,</hi> that He was a perfect and an up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right man; and in all theſe pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces there is the ſame word in the originall, <hi>Tamim:</hi> and <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerus</hi>
                        <pb n="71" facs="tcp:170373:44"/> upon thoſe places in <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſis,</hi> and <hi>Pineda</hi> upon that place in <hi>Job,</hi> interpret this per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection to be the ſimplicity, the integrity, the ſincerity which was in the Hearts of <hi>Noah,</hi> and <hi>Jacob,</hi> and <hi>Job.</hi> For the farther clearing of the word, you know well, there is a twofold perfection: <hi>Impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tata, &amp; Impertita.</hi> A perfection which is imputed to us: and a perfection which is beſtowed upon us; the one is called the Perfection of Juſtification, the other of Sanctification.</p>
                     <p>The former of theſe, in a ſtrict ſenſe, is a compleat per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection. The Saints are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat in Chriſt, they are per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly juſtified, there is not any ſinne left uncovered, nor any
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:170373:45"/> guilt left unwaſhed in the bloud of Chriſt, not the leaſt ſpot but is taken away. By one offering, Chriſt hath perfected for ever them that are Sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, ſayes St. <hi>Paul. Heb.</hi> 10. 14. And then there is a Perfection of Sanctification; and that is called ſo, either in regard of the beginnings of it, or in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of our deſires or aimes at it.</p>
                     <p>The Saints even in this life, have a perfect beginning of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe, as being ſanctified in every part; they are Sanctified throughout, in ſoul, and body, and ſpirit.</p>
                     <p>And then their deſires are high and reall towards perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; they pray, and ſtrive to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due every corruption, to aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:170373:45"/> every known ſinne, to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme every duty. And this is the utmoſt degree of perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that any ſonne of man can attaine to, in this life. And in this reſpect it was that <hi>Job</hi> had the character of a perfect man. Not that he thought himſelfe ſo, in reſpect of an exact obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to the whole law of God; ſo he profeſſes, <hi>If I ſay I am perfect, it ſhall alſo prove me perverſe,</hi> Job. 9. 20. but in reſpect of his deſires, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours towards this perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. <hi>Job</hi> was ſincere, he was ſound at heart, He did not perſonate religion, but was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally a religious perſon. He was <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, as the <hi>Lxx</hi> render that place, <hi>A ſimple man,</hi> that is: plaine hearted, ſingle minded.
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:170373:46"/> He was not a compound, ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king one thing, and meaning another. <hi>Job's</hi> heart might be known by his tongue, and his ſpirit by his actions. And this is the firſt and chiefeſt mark of the perfect man, whom <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid,</hi> in the Text, adviſes us to obſerve and behold.</p>
                     <p>And truly, this perfection in the root, as I have called it, this foundneſſe of heart, is that perfection, which is only valu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able and conſiderable; 'tis that which the Lord ſo often calls for in the Scripture, to love Him, and ſerve Him with all our hearts, that we would not ſuffer our hearts to be divided, and carried away from God, and laid out upon the vanities of the world, while we pretend
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:170373:46"/> to be the ſervants of God in a more ſtrict and purer way then others are.</p>
                     <p>In the ſecond of the <hi>Kings,</hi> ch. 17. v. 33. we read of the Sama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritans, that they feared the Lord, yet ſerved gods of their own. And the prophet <hi>Zephany</hi> reports it as one of the ſins of <hi>Judah,</hi> that they ſware by the Lord, and by <hi>Malcham</hi> the idol of the Ammonites.</p>
                     <p>And I would to God we that call our ſelves, and would be thought, Chriſtians, could purge our hearts from this guilt, that our hearts were per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, and ſincere, and intirely devoted to the ſervice of God. <hi>Beata ſervitus</hi> (ſayes St. <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe) ſi nihil poſſit adverſarius de tuo ſibi ſervitio vendicare,</hi>
                        <pb n="76" facs="tcp:170373:47"/> That's a bleſſed way of ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving God, when Satan can challenge no part in it. How few are there of us that can come to God with <hi>Davids</hi> argument, and may preſs Him as he did, <hi>I am thine, oh ſave me.</hi> The worldly-man can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſay ſo to God, becauſe he hath many Maſters: Luſt comes and ſayes, Thou art mine, for thou makeſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion for the Fleſh, to fulfill the deſires thereof.</p>
                     <p>Covetouſneſſe comes and ſayes, Thou art mine, thou ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt not Chriſt, but thy ſelfe. The Gold and Silver which lyes ruſting in thy coffers, is the portion of the Widdow and the Fatherleſſe. The ſtone in the wall of thine houſe cryes
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:170373:47"/> out, and the beame out of the timber doth anſwer it, and the furrowes in the field joyn in the out-cry, and ſay, We were gotten by oppreſſion, and bribery.</p>
                     <p>Luxury comes and ſayes, Thou art mine, thy conſcience can tell thee, thou haſt ſpent more at a feaſt in one day, then thy charity to the poor hath coſt thee in a whole year; that thou haſt ſtriven to pay moſt at a Reckoning in a Taverne, but haſt pretended excuſes to give nothing to a Briefe in a Church.</p>
                     <p>Ambition comes and ſayes, Thou art mine; thou haſt af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected greatneſſe and power, that thou mighteſt ſinne with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out queſtion or controul; and
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:170373:48"/> then Chriſt will put in his charge too, and ſay; Thou conſidereſt not, that I gave thee a command over men, that thou ſhouldſt obey Me; I honoured thee, that thou ſhouldſt honour Me. Now, <hi>Quem tam multi competunt, quàm vile mancipium eſt?</hi> ſayes that Father St. <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> What a vaſſall, what a ſlave is that man, whoſe heart is challen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged by ſo many maſters? Such an one cannot pretend to <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob's</hi> title, to be <hi>Homo Simplex,</hi> a perfect ſingle-hearted man: He is rather <hi>Homo Multiplex;</hi> St. <hi>James</hi> his <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, doth not reach Him, He is more then a double-minded man, He hath an heart for every luſt, a new God, and a new Religion, when
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:170373:48"/> ſoever the ſway and humour of the times ſhall require it of him.</p>
                     <p>Upon thoſe words of the Lord by his prophet <hi>Joel; Turn unto me with all your heart;</hi> devout <hi>Bernard</hi> hath noted thus: <hi>Corporis converſio, ſi ſola fuerit, nulla erit,</hi> If the body on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly turn to God, and not the heart, there is no converſion. It is but the form of Converſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, there is nothing of truth in it; when there are pretenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to godlyneſſe, but no pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er. He is a miſerable man that contents himſelfe in the outward formalities of religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and neither knows, nor re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gards his heart. <hi>Bernard</hi> apply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed this Note to his monks up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a Faſt-day, and took occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:170373:49"/> to reprove them for their hypocriſie. <hi>Manet tonſura,</hi> (as he goes on) yee continue your ſhavings, yee change not your garment, yee obſerve your rules for faſting, and your hours for prayer; and yet the Lord cryes from heaven, <hi>Cor veſtrum longè eſt à Me,</hi> Your heart not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all this, is far from me.</p>
                     <p>The beſt diſcovery we can make of the integrity and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity of our hearts, is to obſerve the bent and ſway of thoſe foure chiefe affections, Love, Feare, Joy, and Griefe; and ſee whether God or the World have moſt of theſe, and accordingly we may judge our ſelves, whether we are true Converts, or Perfect men.</p>
                     <pb n="81" facs="tcp:170373:49"/>
                     <p> But becauſe the nature of the root, is beſt diſcerned by the fruit which appears on the branches; be pleaſed, that the diſcourſe may paſſe from the firſt mark of perfection, which I call'd perfection in the root, the perfection of the heart, to the ſecond, which is <hi>Integritas Oris,</hi> the Integrity of the Mouth or words; and no mark can be more proper then this, or more naturally conſequent. Our bleſſed Saviour hath given us the rule, <hi>Out of the abundance of the heart the mouth ſpeaketh.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>In the 32<hi rend="sup">d.</hi> Pſalm <hi>David</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounces a bleſſedneſſe upon that man, <hi>in whoſe Spirit there is no guile.</hi> And there are good Expoſitours conceive, this guile to conſiſt in and about
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:170373:50"/> the duty of Repentance, and eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially in the covering of ſinne; as when men ſhall cover their extortions and oppreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons by building an Hoſpitall, and when they ſhall cover all the Week-ſins, with a Sabbaths ſolemnity. Such is ſometimes the folly of Hypocriſy, that it will ſtrive to cover ſin though with a Net, which every man ſees thorow: they will have ſuch mean and pittifull pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences for their unjuſt actions: whereas a perfect-hearted man, is ſerious in the ſearch of his conſcience; and he will take knowledge of his ſins, before they diſcover themſelves; he will acknowledge his riot and voluptuouſneſſe before he burn in a Feaver, occaſioned
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:170373:50"/> by his ſurfeits. He will acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge his wantonneſſe and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centiouſneſſe, before he comes under the anguiſh and ſmart of corroſives. He will acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge his pride and waſtfull<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, before he lye in priſon for debt. The perfect man doth not ſeek his ſins in his belly, nor in his bones, but in his conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. He unfolds that, ripps up that, and enters into the privateſt and remoteſt corners thereof. And he that doth not thus, there is <hi>dolus in Spiritu,</hi> There is guile in his Spirit; and he hath no title to that bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedneſſe, which <hi>David</hi> was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouncing. So that if there be <hi>Veritas in Corde,</hi> Truth in the heart; there will be alſo <hi>Veritas in Ore,</hi> Truth in the mouth:
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:170373:51"/> which being the ſecond mark of a perfect man, give me leave to lay it open to you.</p>
                     <p>The perfection of the Mouth hath a double proſpect; it looks towards God, and towards man. God ſhall have His glory, in the Confeſſion of his ſinne, and man ſhall have his right, in ſpeaking the truth.</p>
                     <p>Among thoſe marks which <hi>David</hi> gives of that happy man, who ſhall dwell in the holy hill of the Lord, this is one: <hi>He ſpeaketh the truth in his heart.</hi> And ſo in the 14 of the <hi>Revel.</hi> v. 5. thoſe bleſſed perſons who are ſaid to follow the Lamb, are thus deſcribed: <hi>In their mouth was found no guile.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Truth, as it is a moſt excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent vertue; ſo it is <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <pb n="85" facs="tcp:170373:51"/> ſaies <hi>Philo:</hi> the moſt ſacred poſſeſſion, pretious and neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary as the Sunne to the world.</p>
                     <p>When the queſtion was put to <hi>Pythagoras,</hi> What that was, in the doing whereof, men might be like unto God, he an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, If they ſpeak the truth. It will be a good in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation of that command of our bleſſed Saviour: <hi>Be ye therefore perfect, as your Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther which is in heaven is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect:</hi> when, as He is truth, ſo we be alwayes carefull to ſpeak the truth from our hearts, <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> even the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then, by the light of nature could conclude, that it was a ſervile <hi>un-ingenuous</hi> humour, <hi>to lye,</hi> and to ſpeak falſely. And we have ſome impreſſion of it
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:170373:52"/> ſtill remaining in us, of all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches we can leaſt brook that: Thou lieſt. How many quarrells hath it occaſion'd? How much blood hath bin ſpilt about it? But truly, 'tis ſad and ſtrange, that men will not endure to be charged with lying, and yet make no conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of lying; that they ſhould take up that part of the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens morality, <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, To ſpeak the truth, is an evidence of a noble, conſtant, well com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed ſpirit; and deſert the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther part of it, by a deficiency in their practice, in yielding themſelves up to tell lies for advantage.</p>
                     <p>Some Divines have moved and debated theſe two Caſes: Whether if a man be examined
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:170373:52"/> before a Competent Judge, he may not lye to preſerve himſelfe or his Friend from the penalty of the Law. And 'tis anſwer'd in the negative: He may not lye. There can no caſe be put, in which it may be lawfull for any man to lye to any man: not to a mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>night, not to a noon-thiefe, that aſſaults his houſe, or his perſon, he may not lye. And although many have put names of diſguiſe upon ſuch practiſes, and call them Equivocations and Reſervations, yet they are all children of the ſame Father the Devill, who is the father of lies.</p>
                     <p>The other Caſe is: Whether if a man be examined before an incompetent Judge, he may
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:170373:53"/> not equivocate and prevaricate with Him? And 'tis anſwer'd thus: that if he do ſpeak, he muſt ſpeak the truth. They al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, that to an incompetent Judge, that hath no legall power to examine him, he may be ſilent without ſinne: but to a competent Judge, 'tis an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>defenſible ſinne either to be ſilent, or to depoſe an untruth.</p>
                     <p>And upon this account, ſince it is ſo clearly ſinfull in a wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, either to prevaricate or to depoſe an untruth; I ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit it to your grave Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, whether it be not high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conſiderable, for an Advo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate to plead an untruth; by the advantage of his Rheto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick and Eloquence to palliate ſuch a cauſe, which, in his owne
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:170373:53"/> conſcience and opinion, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves rather a puniſhment then a defence; whether in pleading ſuch cauſes, they do not take part with evill doers, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage men to venture upon unjuſt actions, ſince they may be aſſured, that for a fee, they may have a ſubtle and ingeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Advocate, to maintain their cauſe. But in this caſe, ſince I ſpeak to ſuch, whoſe piety and integrity, I have no reaſon either to queſtion or ſuſpect, I ſhall proceed no fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
                     <p>Indeed, my deſigne lyes mainely againſt that ſort of men, who inure their tongues, to ſpeak malitiouſly and defa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matorily, and blaſt the fair re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation of their neighbour,
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:170373:54"/> by falſe ſuggeſtions and inſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuations.</p>
                     <p>It may be ſometimes unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, to ſpeak all that a man knowes to be true of his neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour; but it is alwayes unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to ſpeak that which he knows to be falſe. This is <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, <hi>calumnia,</hi> ſuch a practice whence the Devill takes his name, <hi>Diabolus,</hi> an accuſer: 'tis a deviliſh practice by falſe informations and ſlanders to repreſent a man worſe then he is, and to expoſe Him either to the hatred of the common people, or the cenſure of the Magiſtrate, for crimes whereof he was never guilty. Like the Heathens of old, who put the Chriſtians into the skinnes of beaſts, and then brought them
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:170373:54"/> forth to be torn and worried, ſuch an artifice hath <hi>Satan</hi> uſed all along, by ſuborning foul tongues, to ſully and ſtaine the fame and reputation of men, thereby to prepare them for deſtruction. When <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Silas</hi> were miſreported to the Romane Magiſtrates, as trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blers of the City, and teachers of cuſtomes, which were not lawfull to be obſerved; we may wonder the leſſe, that they were beaten and impriſoned: yea, we ſee it in a greater ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, in our bleſſed Saviour Himſelfe; when He was ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd to be a deceiver of the people, a wine-bibber, a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panion of publicans and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, and one that had a Devill, theſe aſperſions raiſ'd the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:170373:55"/> of the common people, and the malice of the Jewes was leſſe diſcernable, when they cryed away with Him, cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifie Him: and you know what the iſſue was, the murder of the Lord of life.</p>
                     <p>I ſhall not need to urge any arguments to prove how farre diſtant a back-biter or a ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derer is from a perfect man. That grave Authour <hi>Pariſienſis</hi> calls him, <hi>Dentem Diaboli,</hi> The tooth of the Divell, which he faſtens in an innocent perſon, and tears his good name, and perchance his eſtate too, cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and unmercifully, and irrepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably. We may eaſily conclude the ſin is great when the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is ſo heavy, when both St. <hi>Paul</hi> and St. <hi>John</hi> tell us,
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:170373:55"/> that whoſoever are revilers, and makers of lyes, ſhall not enter into the new Jeruſalem, the Kingdome of God.</p>
                     <p>There remaines yet the third mark of this perfect man to be conſidered, and that is, <hi>Integritas Operis,</hi> His Equity and Uprightneſſe in all his Actions.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Pineda</hi> tells us that the ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall term, <hi>Jaſar;</hi> which, in that place of <hi>Job,</hi> is rendered <hi>upright;</hi> ſigniſies ſometimes <hi>Jucundum eſse:</hi> and then the up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right man will be ſuch an one, as is of a complacent humour, of a mild and ſoft temper. And probably <hi>Apollinarius</hi> had reſpect to this ſenſe of the word, when he metaphraſ'd our text, <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, Keep
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:170373:56"/> meekneſſe, and then it may mean, Be neither ſowre not bitter in looks or language; be not harſh or cruell in thy dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings or actions with men.</p>
                     <p>I obſerve in moſt Latine Tranſlations, that they retain the word <hi>Rectum.</hi> In an old Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuſcript I read it, <hi>Cuſtodi ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicitatem &amp; vitae rectum:</hi> and <hi>Pineda</hi> by many inſtances clears it, that <hi>Jaſar</hi> ſignifies <hi>Planiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>em viae,</hi> the ſmoothneſſe and evenneſſe of a way. And then by a fair alluſion it may import that Juſtice and Equity which men ought to uſe in all their dealings and commerce. There is no trouble in walking in a plain way. When there are hills to ſtrain the nerves, or valleys to endanger a precipice; hence
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:170373:56"/> ariſes the trouble of a Jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney.</p>
                     <p>And ſo it is in civill com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce: when we are to deal with a plain man, whoſe words and actions are both of the ſame piece, who lyes not upon the catch, and hath not his ſubtle reſerves, of falſe weights, or lights, or meaſures; there is neither feare nor danger in converſing with ſuch a man. If we look into the body of this 37 Pſalm, we ſhall find <hi>David</hi> inſtancing in ſome actions, which ſeem to be contrary to this uprightneſſe, which I am to preſent to you.</p>
                     <p>In the 12 verſe, he ſpeaks of plotting againſt the Juſt. In the 14 verſe, of drawing the ſword, and bending the bow
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:170373:57"/> againſt the poore and needy: In the 21 verſe, of borrowing and not paying againe. And ſo farre forth as any man is plung'd in the guilt of thoſe practiſes, he is ſo farre diſtant from true uprightneſſe. Will you pleaſe to review theſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances.</p>
                     <p>Firſt, What is it to plot a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Juſt man? I reſt in <hi>Lorinus</hi> his opinion upon the place: It is to pick a quarrell with him about his Religion, and the worſhip of his God: ſuch enemies we find the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Daniel</hi> met with. They ſaid among themſelves, We ſhall not find any occaſion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt this <hi>Daniel,</hi> except we find it againſt him concerning the Law of his God. So we
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:170373:57"/> read, <hi>Luke</hi> the ſixth, That the Phariſees watched our Saviour, that they might have an accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation againſt him. So true is that of <hi>Solomon, He that is up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right in the way, is an abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the wicked, Prov.</hi> 29. 27. But this is certainely an abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable kind of wickedneſſe, when the worſhip of God ſhall be made the occaſion of envie. When, like <hi>Cain,</hi> they ſhall hate, and riſe up againſt their brother, becauſe he offers to God a better ſacrifice then themſelves. It was a pious wiſh that of <hi>Bucolcerus: Mortuus est Cain: ſed utinam non viveret in filiis ſuis. Cain</hi> is dead: but would to God he did not live ſtill in his ſonnes; who carry ſtill his bloody club, wreaking
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:170373:58"/> in the gore of Chriſtians, and ſeeking the deſtruction of thoſe, that are more holy then themſelves.</p>
                     <p>It is a ſad thing, when men ſhall come into the houſe of God, as <hi>Doeg</hi> did into the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle; and to returne an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>former againſt the Miniſter, as he did againſt <hi>Abimelech.</hi> Any plot againſt a juſt man, argues rather pride then perfection: He is an ill ſubject to Chriſt, who envies Him the glory of a populous Kingdome.</p>
                     <p>Conſider the ſecond inſtance: The drawing the ſword, and bending the bow againſt the poore and needy. Expoſitours conceive that <hi>David</hi> in this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, points at <hi>Saul,</hi> and thoſe ſeverall acts of injuſtice,
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:170373:58"/> whereby he oppreſſed him. It is no new thing to ſee Right overcome by Might, and <hi>Ahab</hi> ſolacing himſelfe in <hi>Naboth's</hi> vineyard</p>
                     <p>Notwithſtanding Holy <hi>Job,</hi> and the Prophets <hi>Jeremy</hi> and <hi>Habaccuck</hi> have expoſtulated the caſe with God, concerning the proſperity of the wicked; yet in his infinite wiſedome he ſees it fit to continue it, and ſtill we ſee the poor and needy, become a prey to the rich and mighty. But theſe permiſſive acts of Providence are no war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, or ſecurity for ſuch acts of Injuſtice. He is far from a perfect man, who ſeeks to ſlay the upright, or, as <hi>Solomon</hi> ſpeaks, Robs the poor becauſe he is poor, and unable to help himſelfe.</p>
                     <pb n="100" facs="tcp:170373:59"/>
                     <p> The third inſtance is: <hi>The wicked borroweeh and payeth not againe.</hi> In which is noted an high act of injuſtice, and contrary to that Evangelicall precept delivered by St. <hi>Paul, Owe nothing to any man but love;</hi> provided alwayes, there be ſufficiency and ability to pay. Whoſoever ſhall pretend poverty to his creditour, and make a fraudulent compoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, contracts upon his owne ſoul the guilt of theft in an high degree. And ſome have been ſo curious to make the obſervation, That eſtates com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded for, ſeldome proſper: there is for the moſt part ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of fraud and conceal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and that conſtitutes the wicked man, whom <hi>David</hi> here
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:170373:59"/> points at, <hi>He borroweth and pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not again.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>You ſee in common experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, how the Courts of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice are troubled and peſtered with ſuits and cauſes in theſe caſes; with actions in regard of conſpiracy, The wicked plotting againſt the Juſt; with actions of treſpaſſe and battery, The drawing his ſword againſt the poor, and by might oppreſſing Him; and with actions of debt, The wicked borroweth and paying not again.</p>
                     <p>And no doubt, <hi>David</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring to winne, and work up the ſouls of men, to this per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection and uprightneſſe, hath proceeded in that Method throughout this Pſalme, as it were Antiphonically, and by
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:170373:60"/> way of contra-poſition, to ſet down the Characters of the upright and the wicked man, and deſcribe them by their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions, by their words, and by their actions. Of ſo much concernment did <hi>David</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive it to be, exactly to know the perfect and the upright man.</p>
                     <p>And in all this diſcourſe, I have purſued the ſame method: as contraries are beſt diſcern'd when they are placed together; ſo in every mark of this perfect man, you have had ſomething poſitively, ſomething negative<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly delivered. And now that I have preſented the Object be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you, in which the great part of my buſineſſe lay, I am now to invite you to the Act:
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:170373:60"/> To <hi>mark and</hi> to <hi>behold him,</hi> which was the ſecond part I propoſed to obſerve.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="part">
                     <head>The ſecond part: The Act.</head>
                     <p>But I need not detaine you long in this Act. I do not find any Expoſitour whom I have conſulted, that ſtops upon it. <hi>Mollerus</hi> conceives, that <hi>David</hi> onely calls upon us to obſerve the paſſages of Divine Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, and the various iſſues of his Diſpenſations, concerning the wayes and the ends of the wicked, and the perfect man. It is the humour, or rather the weakneſſe, of moſt men to judge outward appearances, and to conclude a man either Happy or Miſerable, according
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:170373:61"/> to his ſucceſſes in this world So <hi>Job's</hi> friends paſſed their cenſures upon Him, and he muſt needs be a diſſembling Hypocrite, becauſe He was ſo grievouſly afflicted.</p>
                     <p>But this, according to that ſaying of our Saviour, was un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteous Judgement. And as <hi>David</hi> had made his obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation concerning the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous man, I have been young but now am old: yet I never ſaw the righteous forſaken, nor his ſeed begging their bread, ſo he calls upon all others to make the like obſervation con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the perfect man. Mark and behold Him (ſayes He) And although ye may ſee the wicked flouriſhing like a bay tree, and the upright man
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:170373:61"/> withering like a ſhrub; the one in honour and flowing with all temporall abundancies, the other vile and deſpiſed, and lacking neceſſaries, yet judge not: They are yet upon their way; they are not yet come to their journeys end; they are now buſied in their ſeverall works, and have not received their wages: but when the day of our life ſhall begin to cloſe, and the ſhaddowes of death ſhall ſpread themſelves; and the grave begin to open her mouth; and the Arch-angell's trumpet, in a paſſing bell, ſhall ſummon the ſonnes of men to Judgement, then will be fulfilled that of the Prophet <hi>Malachi: At that time God will make up his Jewells, and</hi>
                        <pb n="106" facs="tcp:170373:62"/> 
                        <hi>men ſhall diſcern between the righteous and the wicked, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween him that ſerveth God, and him that ſerveth him not, Chap.</hi> 3. <hi>verſ.</hi> 17, 18.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="part">
                     <head>The third part: The reaſon of the Act.</head>
                     <p>And now, here, enters our third part, for the concluſion of all. Marke and behold the perfect man, for he is worthy of your obſervation. <hi>The end of that man is peace.</hi> Our bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Saviour ſpeaking of <hi>John</hi> the Baptiſt: What (ſaith He) went yee out into the wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to ſee? A reed ſhaken with the wind? It may be in the eyes of ſome that ſaw him, he ſeemed not much more
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:170373:62"/> conſiderable: but I tell you; <hi>He is a Prophet, and more then a Prophet.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>And if any prophane ſpirit ſhould ſay; What do you call us to mark and behold? bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken reeds? and ſmoaking flax? perſons that have lived in trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and are dying in diſhon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our? ſuch as have been the ſubject of wanton wits to make Songs of, and the object of mens hatred and ſcorn? Such indeed is the lot and portion of the upright man: yet let me tell you, he is ſomewhat more, yea very much more then he is conceived to be. Though the Wicked raiſe warre againſt him, yet He is the Son of peace; though he ſayle through a rough Sea, yet he hath a calm
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:170373:63"/> haven, though he meet with croſſes on his way, yet he ſhall find comforts in his end. And herein lyes the weight of the reaſon, and upon which the ſtate of the perfect man be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes ſo worthy of all obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation.</p>
                     <p>Man as he is a rational crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, propoſes to himſelf ſome end in all his actions. That's the great wheel that moves him, and ſets him to work; and whatſoever he propoſes to himſelf as his end, that in his preſent ſenſe and opinion, hath an appearance of Good. Thoſe two maxims in Philoſophy conſiſt well together. <hi>Omnia agunt propter finem,</hi> and <hi>Omnia appetunt Bonum.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>But now it oft-times comes
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:170373:63"/> to paſſe, that there is a ſad miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carriage; men project one thing, and another falls out. There is <hi>Finis Operis,</hi> &amp; <hi>Finis Operantis.</hi> The end which is properly conſequent to the Work: And the end which is in the deſign of the Workman. And theſe doe oftentimes differ: Men engage themſelves into ſinfull actions, and propoſe to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves as their End, pleaſures, or profits, or preferments: this is <hi>Finis Operantis,</hi> the end of the workman; but this is not <hi>Finis Operis,</hi> the end of the worke: <hi>For, the wages of ſinne is death,</hi> In the eighth of the prophecy of <hi>Amos,</hi> the Lord threatens his people <hi>Iſrael</hi> for their op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion and prophanneſſe: <hi>Hear this ye that ſwallow up the</hi>
                        <pb n="110" facs="tcp:170373:64"/> 
                        <hi>needy. I will turn your feasts into mourning, I will make it as the mourning for an only Son: and the end thereof as a bitter day,</hi> at the 10 verſe.</p>
                     <p>This bitter day was the end properly conſequent to the worke of ſinne, though they projected and deſign'd ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, namely their private gain and advantage.</p>
                     <p>Let us remember then what the prophet <hi>Iſay</hi> hath taught us. The worke of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe ſhall be peace, and the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect of righteouſneſſe, quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and aſſurance for ever, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 32. 17.</p>
                     <p>But we muſt not underſtand this word, Peace, in that lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude as it was uſually taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Jewes, for a conflu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:170373:64"/> of all temporall bleſſings, as it happened in the caſe of <hi>Job,</hi> whoſe latter end the Lord made better then his begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, that is, in reſpect of tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall abundances, having his eſtate doubled to him. We muſt take it in that ſenſe, as it means peace of conſcience, and an aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance of the favour of God in Chriſt, that however mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters goe with him in reſpect of his perſon, or eſtate, or his life, or his poſterity, he reſts ſecure as for the ſtate of his Soul; and can with cheerfulneſſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend it into the hands of his faithfull Creatour.</p>
                     <p>Whereas the ſame prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> tells us, <hi>There is no peace to the wicked, Iſa.</hi> 57. 21. Such as do not walke in the wayes of
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:170373:65"/> peace, ſhall never find peace at their End. I deny not but a Wicked man may dye poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſ'd of all the comforts this world can afford him; he may dye (as it was ſaid of <hi>David)</hi> full of dayes, riches, and hon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, and yet his death-bed pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low may be uneaſie to him, when it ſhall come to that of the Poet <hi>Linquenda domus &amp; tellus,</hi> &amp;c. when he ſhall look upon thoſe things, which we call worldly comforts, but find no comfort in them.</p>
                     <p>When he ſhall look upon his eſtate, and not only grieve that he muſt part from it himſelfe, but he muſt leave it to a Son, whom, as <hi>Solomon</hi> ſpeaks, he doth not know whether he ſhall be a fool.</p>
                     <pb n="113" facs="tcp:170373:65"/>
                     <p> When he ſhall look upon his Wife and Children, and take his laſt farewell, and out of the horrour of his conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence ſhall be forced to declare himſelfe thus. I leave a great Eſtate amongſt you, but I fear, you will finde it encumbred with the curſe and vengeance of God.</p>
                     <p>When he ſhall look upon his friends, that ſtand weeping and mourning over him, and ſhall breathe out <hi>Socrates</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint in that ſenſe, <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, Oh Friends, ye cannot help me, your counſel, nor your power cannot enlarge the terme of my life a minute, nor give a ranſome unto God for mee.</p>
                     <p>When he ſhall look upon
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:170373:66"/> his body waſted, and confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by his Luxuries, and, it may be, ſo diſeaſed, as to be loath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome to himſelfe and his atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dants; and from a ſad reflecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on upon the vanities of his life paſt, ſhall ſigh and groan out this as his own Epitaph; <hi>I have lived in ſinne, and now I lye down in ſorrow.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>But above all, when he ſhall conſider the ſtate of his poor Soul, whoſe immortall nature delivers him up to an Eternity either of bliſs or miſery. When this poor Soul, poor I ſay as not being rich in faith, or any other ſpirituall grace, ſhall ſit upon his lips, as the Emperour <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drian's</hi> did, with a <hi>Quò nunc ibo?</hi> whither ſhall I go? what ſhall become of me? How ſhall I ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:170373:66"/> before God, whoſe Name and Sabbaths I have blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phem'd and prophan'd? How ſhall I ſtand before Chriſt, whoſe Miniſters and Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces I have perſecuted and deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſed? What comfort can I expect, or hope for, from the holy Ghoſt, whoſe private mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and workings in my heart I have ſleighted and reſiſted? I never look'd upon, nor ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amin'd my heart or wayes, by ſaying, What have I done? And now, miſerable man that I am, I know not what to do.</p>
                     <p>Oh my Chriſtian brethren, let us think upon theſe things; this will be the certaine Fate of a dying wicked man. The Lord will be juſt and righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous though we are not, and
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:170373:67"/> every ſecure ſinner ſhall feel in his conſcience <hi>Futuri Judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cii praejudicium,</hi> as <hi>Tertullian</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſes it, a taſte of that eternal Judgment and Horrour, which he muſt endure irremediably and everlaſtingly.</p>
                     <p>Think upon the ſad ſtate of <hi>Cain.</hi> We cannot tell by the Hebrew, whether he ſaid; My iniquity, or, my puniſhment, is greater then I can bear. Think upon the ſad ſtate of <hi>Antiochus:</hi> when he lay dying, he calls to his friends, and ſayes, My heart faileth me, into what floods of miſery am I fallen? and now I remember the evills that I have done at <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Think upon the ſad ſtate of <hi>Saul:</hi> when he was diſcomfited by the Philiſtines, he calls to
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:170373:67"/> his ſervant; <hi>Stand upon me I pray thee, and kill me, for anguiſh is come upon me.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>And let theſe terrours of the Lord convince us, that this perfection and uprightneſſe in our hearts, and words, and acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, is a conſiderable quality. Let us with all poſſible ſpeed and care provide for our death<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed comfort, and purge our conſciences by Confeſſion, and Faith, and Repentance and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution; that we may ſtop their Mouths, and ſtill their Clamour, and not become, as <hi>Job</hi> complained, a burden to our ſelves. <hi>Job</hi> 7. 20.</p>
                     <p>It was a good Caution that <hi>Bernard</hi> gave <hi>Eugenius; Nullus moleſtior oculus ſuo cujuſque.</hi> Through the guilt of ſinne, it
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:170373:68"/> will ſo come to paſſe, that no eye will be ſo dreadfull and terrible to us, as our owne; there will not be a face either in Heaven or Earth, which a troubled conſcience would ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther fly from than his owne, and can leſſe do it.</p>
                     <p>The Lawes of God are the rules of that perfection and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightneſſe, which in St. <hi>Pauls</hi> phraſe we ſhould follow and preſſe after.</p>
                     <p>And Holy <hi>David</hi> tells us that their peace will be great that love, and are not offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded at the lawes of God. This peace in our laſt ſickneſſe will prove our beſt Cordiall. It was ſo to King <hi>Hezekiah,</hi> when the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> brought to him that ſad meſſage: Thou ſhalt
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:170373:68"/> dye, and not live: He betakes himſelfe to prayer: Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber now, Oh Lord, I beſeech thee, how I have walked before thee in truth, and with a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect heart, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 38. 3. It was not his Crown, or his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, nor thoſe vaſt Treaſures he ſtood poſſeſſ'd of, that then adminiſtred any comfort to him, onely the teſtimony of a good conſcience, that he had walked before the Lord in truth and uprightneſſe.</p>
                     <p>Wherefore it is a ſad thing, ſo many men ſhould ſeek after Science, ſo few after Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence; that men ſhould hunger and thirſt after Riches, and not after Righteouſneſſe: whereas did we beſtow as much paines in ſeeking Morall and Theolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gicall
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:170373:69"/> Vertues and Graces, as we do for Arts and Sciences, we might attaine them ſooner, and retaine them longer.</p>
                     <p>Longer, did I ſay? I need not recall the word: Spirituall graces are truly called a trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, becauſe as they ſupply to all purpoſes, ſo they continue to all times. Grace carries us through all duties, and through all tryalls. It makes the yoak of Chriſt eaſie, and his burden light; it weakens the ſtrength of ſinne, and takes out the ſting of death; it ſtuſſes our pillows with the Feathers of a Dove, and fills us with thoſe joyes that are ſo unſpeakeable and glorious. St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of the primitive Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans: <hi>Quidam patienter vivunt,</hi>
                        <pb n="121" facs="tcp:170373:69"/> 
                        <hi>&amp; delectabiliter moriuntur:</hi> They live with patience, and they dye with joy. Their Life it ſeemes was a trouble, Death an advantage: they endured the one, and deſired the other. That bleſſed Martyr <hi>Vincentius,</hi> had doubtleſſe a great meaſure of this bleſſed peace in his end, when he could ſay to his exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutioner <hi>Dacianus; Nunquam aliquis adeò benè ſervivit mihi, ut tu;</hi> No man ever did me ſo good ſervice as you are about to do: your torments will ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten me to my triumphs, your ſword will but let out that corruption of fleſh and blood, which cannot inherit the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God.</p>
                     <p>I ſhall conclude and diſmiſſe you in the comfort of that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:170373:70"/> recorded by Holy <hi>David</hi> in the 64. <hi>Pſalme. All the up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right in heart ſhall glory,</hi> at the 10 verſe.</p>
                     <p>The ſubject of the promiſe you ſee, is Glory: and the perſons to whom it is due, are the Upright in heart. And we may admire the wiſdome and goodneſſe of the Holy Ghoſt in that expreſſion: (upright in heart.) A man may be upright in the deſires of his heart, when through the ſuddaineſſe or vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence of a temptation, he may be over-borne into a ſinne. The Lord help us, we cannot maintaine a perfect rectitude in the wayes of this world. In every calling there are ſome in-evitable temptations: but yet let us ſtrive and beare up,
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:170373:70"/> though the ſtream of corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion runne ſtrong againſt us, let us put off all diſguiſes in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and lay down the love of craft, and falſe-hood, and circumvention in Civill actions; and then we ſhall ſecure our title to the promiſe. Of what? Of glory. So we read it; but tranſlations differ: ſome have it, <hi>Laudabuntur,</hi> they ſhall be prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. Uprightneſſe is ſuch a grace as creates an Holy and Reverentiall admiration in all that behold it. Even wicked <hi>Balaam</hi> could wiſh, Let me dye the death of the righteous, and let my laſt end be like the <hi>Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el</hi> of God. But I reſt not in that. Take the word in another tranſlation; <hi>Laetabuntur,</hi> they
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:170373:71"/> ſhall rejoyce. If we could crowd Heaven into a Map, we might find two Hemi-ſphears; the one would be Joy, the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther would be Glory: And as of thoſe two Hemiſphears of the world, the firſt hath been known long before: The o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther (that of <hi>America</hi> which is the richer in treaſure) God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved for latter diſcoveries: ſo though he reſerve that He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſphear of heaven, which is the Glory thereof, to the reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection; yet the other Hemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſphear, the Joy of heaven, God opens to our diſcovery, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livers for our habitation, even whilſt we dwell in this world. That which Chriſt ſhall ſay to our ſouls at the laſt Judgment;
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:170373:71"/> 
                        <hi>Enter into your Maſter's joy;</hi> He ſayes to our Conſcience now, Enter in your Maſter's joy. The everlaſtingneſſe of the Joy, is the bleſſedneſſe of the next Life; but the entring, the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choation is afforded to the up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right in this. Thoſe words of Chriſt, <hi>Come ye bleſſed,</hi> are words intended to them that are comming to Him, that are upon their way. And as here he bids us, Come; herafter, he will bid us, Welcome.</p>
                     <p>Let it not trouble you then, what I told you out of <hi>Solomon,</hi> that the upright is an abhomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation to the wicked, and ſo, tribulations are to be expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. But you know, as a man muſt have ſome land, or he
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:170373:72"/> cannot be in wardſhip: ſo a man muſt have ſome of the love of God, or elſe he could not fall under Gods correction. And when the hand of God lies upon him, either in a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe, or in a perſecution, and preſſes him, ſo that even life it ſelfe is expiring, then he ſhall feel the comfort of this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe: <hi>Laetabitur,</hi> he ſhall Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce. And as the Lord ſaid concerning the reducing of his people <hi>Iſrael</hi> out of <hi>Babylon: Sibilabo populum meum,</hi> I will hiſſe for them, <hi>Zech.</hi> 10. 8. ſo when the upright man ſhall lye panting, and languiſhing upon his bed of ſickneſſe. The Lord ſhal then come to his bed-ſide, and hiſſe for him, and whiſper
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:170373:72"/> gently to his departing ſoul: Feare not Sin, I am thy Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe: Feare not Death, I am the Reſurrection: Feare not the day of Judgment, I am thy Advocate now, and ſhall be thy Judge then. And by theſe flaſhes of joy, ſhall ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighten his ſoul, as to overcome all the cares and the feares of Nature, all the Horrour of the paſſing Bell, all the cryes, and teares of a diſtracted and ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering family. Like bleſſed <hi>Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phen,</hi> he ſhall, by the eye of Faith, ſee Heaven open, and his Saviour ſtanding at the right hand of God. And his joy then ſhall be ſo ſtrong, as that it ſhall no more extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh, or evaporate than his
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:170373:73"/> ſoul ſhall. And it ſhall become a Joy that ſhall paſſe up, and put on a more glorious garment above, and be a Joy ſuper-in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſted in Glory.</p>
                  </div>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
                  <pb facs="tcp:170373:73"/>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
